<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>awareness | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/awareness/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/awareness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>awareness</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>awareness</title>
      <link>/tags/awareness/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring For Operational Awareness</title>
      <link>/post/monitoring-for-operational-awareness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/monitoring-for-operational-awareness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sustainably achieving an appropriate level of reliability first requires that
you know what’s going on with your systems and services. You find that out by
monitoring. Before you can effectively monitor for reliability, however, you
must have a reasonable level of operational awareness. This means you need to
understand how systems in production are functioning in order to work toward
reliability of those systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s production environments and the paths by which we deploy systems and
applications are complex. Thus, it is not uncommon to have to do a bit of
discovery to obtain an operational awareness baseline. Some questions to ask
include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What exactly is running in production?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a specific application, what are its component parts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of those parts communicate with which other parts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some more complex factors that you’ll want to examine to give you
a better understanding of your systems and services and how to make them more
reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the app or service perform in the past?&lt;/strong&gt; It’s true that “past
performance is no guarantee of future results.” However, knowledge about
past performance can be useful in calibrating expectations, and awareness of
past outages can provide you with a sense of potential failure modes that
you should incorporate into your thought processes around reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the socio-technical context?&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, who owns or cares
about the service or app? How did it get deployed? Information about the
stakeholders, as well as knowing, for example, whether it was deployed by
hand or via an automated process can have many ramifications when we begin
to make updates to improve reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to all these questions will help you to build a baseline around
“normal” behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/monitoring-for-reliability/&#34;&gt;Monitoring For Reliability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
