<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>coordination | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/coordination/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/coordination/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>coordination</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>coordination</title>
      <link>/tags/coordination/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing Communication Channels</title>
      <link>/post/establishing-communications-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/establishing-communications-channel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To address some of the challenges around how we communicate we also want to find a way to create a unique channel or space for engineers to discuss the details of the incident - a “conversation bridge” in our persistent group chat tool -which for Tailwind Traders is Microsoft Teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want a channel that is unique to the incident only. We do not want conversations about other engineering efforts.We don’t want conversations about what people are doing for lunch. We ONLY want conversations related to the incident. Because then we can take that text (or data) and analyze later in a Post-incident review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/understanding-why-we-learn-from-incidents/&#34;&gt;Understanding Why We Learn From Incidents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing On-call Roles</title>
      <link>/post/establishing-oncall-roles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/establishing-oncall-roles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Creating a repeatable response plan means establishing who does what when something goes wrong. We don&amp;rsquo;t want there to be any question around who is supposed to be doing what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, it is important to establish roles and the associated expectations. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a separation of duties exercise. In fact, we want to encourage less of that. It is however, a way of establishing better coordination and communication. It prevents people from stepping on each others toes while enabling cross-collaboration amongst not only on-call rosters, but an entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first role we need to talk about is the &lt;strong&gt;Primary Responder&lt;/strong&gt; – the Primary “On-call” engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This person is expected to acknowledge their awareness of an incident once the alert has been received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we have the &lt;strong&gt;secondary responder&lt;/strong&gt; – who is there as back up -Another engineer who can step in if the primary responder is unavailable or unreachable. Or if they just need another pair of eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key role to identify, in many cases, is the &lt;strong&gt;incident commander&lt;/strong&gt;. An incident commander can be extremely helpful when you have got a large-scale outage that effects a lot of different components or requires coordination across many teams and different systems. They are great for making sure that engineers stay focused and they are working on their own remediation efforts&amp;hellip; Ensuring people are not stepping on each other or undoing each other&amp;rsquo;s work.  It is good to have a central person who can track what is going on and who is doing what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Communication Coordinator&lt;/strong&gt; is meant to be the person working in conjunction with the incident commander to share more information beyond those who are in the firefight actively working to recover from the incident itself. That could be customers. It could be the sales and marketing teams. Maybe your customer support. There are many people within an organization who need to be made aware of what’s taking place and the status around how things are progressing. It&amp;rsquo;s always good to put someone in charge of managing that communication and making sure that other stakeholders are aware of what is happening and what’s being done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;scribe&lt;/strong&gt;’s role is to document the conversation in as much detail as possible. Teams commonly use phone bridges, conference calls, or video chat to get everyone together and try to understand what is going on, which can certainly help create space for the conversation. However, it is difficult for us to go through and understand in detail what the engineers were saying and doing unless it is transcribed. As a result, a scribe is that person who can help us document as much as possible to review later. What were people saying, doing, feeling, and even experiencing?  It is all data to be analyzed – but only if we capture it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s quite common within on-call rosters to identify &lt;strong&gt;subject matter experts&lt;/strong&gt;, so that early responders know who to escalate too quickly. These people should not be on call all the time, of course, but we do want to be able to identify who is our database expert. Who is our front-end expert? Who are the people that we can reach out to if our primary and secondary responders are not able to diagnose and resolve the issue themselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a closer look at each of these roles to better understand their place within our incident response efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/identifying-the-primary-responder/&#34;&gt;Identifying the Primary Responder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing On-call Rosters</title>
      <link>/post/establishing-oncall-rosters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/establishing-oncall-rosters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rosters establish a framework around who is on-call at any given point. A roster, or team, is made up of multiple engineers. Rosters can also contain multiple rotations. I&amp;rsquo;m testing out how to edit a page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/creating-an-oncall-roster-using-azure-table-storage/&#34;&gt;Creating an on-call roster using Azure Table Storage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing On-call Rotations</title>
      <link>/post/establishing-oncall-rotations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/establishing-oncall-rotations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;em&gt;on-call&lt;/em&gt; for long periods of time. It&amp;rsquo;s detrimental to their health and therefore the systems they create and look after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make sure people aren&amp;rsquo;t expected to respond to problems 24-hours a day, indefinitely, we use rotations. Also referred to as scheduled shifts. That way people can take turns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being on-call requires a heavy cognitive task which then negatively impacts many aspects of a person&amp;rsquo;s life. Shifts allow engineers to take “on-call” responsibility for their own specific recurring rotation and share the load in a way that keeps the human element a priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Site Reliability Engineering is an engineering discipline devoted to helping an organization &lt;strong&gt;sustainably&lt;/strong&gt; achieve the appropriate level of reliability in their systems, services, and products. Long periods of on-call responsibilities is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When creating shifts there are a number of common approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;24-x-7&#34;&gt;24 x 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of rotations used by teams are known as 27 x 7 shifts where engineers will be “on-call” for several days in a row. However, most “Elite/High performers” would agree that rotations longer than 3 or 4 days are detrimental to the overall health of engineering staff and therefore the entire system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-the-sun&#34;&gt;Follow the Sun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the sun shifts are nice for distributed teams. These allow for engineers to schedule their “on-call” shifts only during their normal working office hours. As they end their day and go home, engineers in a different time zone can take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, there are many ways to customize shifts, especially for weekends when engineers need more flexibility. Engineers should be able to hand off the role to someone when personal conflicts arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once roles, rosters, and rotations have been determined and put in place, we can now focus our attion on methods of 
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/tracking-incident-details/&#34;&gt;Tracking Incident Details&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Communication Coordinator</title>
      <link>/post/identifying-the-communication-coordinator/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/identifying-the-communication-coordinator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Communication Coordinator is meant to be the person working in conjunction with the incident commander to share more information beyond those who are in the firefight actively working to recover from the incident itself. That could be customers. It could be the sales and marketing teams. Maybe your customer support. There are many people within an organization who need to be made aware of what’s taking place and the status around how things are progressing. It&amp;rsquo;s always good to put someone in charge of managing that communication and making sure that other stakeholders are aware of what is happening and what’s being done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/identifying-the-scribe/&#34;&gt;Identifying The Scribe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Incident Commander</title>
      <link>/post/identifying-the-incident-commander/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/identifying-the-incident-commander/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another key role to identify, in many cases, is the incident commander. An incident commander can be extremely helpful when you have got a large-scale outage that effects a lot of different components or requires coordination across many teams and different systems. They are great for making sure that engineers stay focused and they are working on their own remediation efforts&amp;hellip; Ensuring people are not stepping on each other or undoing each other&amp;rsquo;s work.  It is good to have a central person who can track what is going on and who is doing what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/identifying-the-communication-coordinator/&#34;&gt;Identifying the Communication Coordinator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
