<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>learning | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>learning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>learning</title>
      <link>/tags/learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Why We Learn From Incidents</title>
      <link>/post/understanding-why-we-learn-from-incidents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/understanding-why-we-learn-from-incidents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Incident response doesn’t stop when the incident is over. They say those who
don’t study history are doomed to repeat it. Likewise, those who don’t study,
analyze, and learn from the incidents they resolved are doomed to keep repeating
the process, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your most important means of learning from incidents is the post-incident
review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an incident occurs, your first reaction probably isn’t, “Hurray – a
learning opportunity!” Your immediate priority is figuring out what went wrong
and fixing it as quickly as possible, to reduce the impact on your customers and
end users – as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once the incident has been resolved, it’s important to follow up and
benefit from the discovery of whatever mistakes or circumstances led to the
failure. Doing so will help you prevent the same thing from happening again and
will also help you understand what tactics do and don’t work best when
responding to any kind of incident in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-incident review is part of the analysis phase of the incident response
lifecycle. Not all post-incident reviews are created equal. There are different
ways to approach the process, and too much focus on certain aspects of the
problem or framing questions in the wrong way can reduce the value of the
review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to now explore the best path towards generating actionable introspection about the systems we co-create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/understanding-how-complex-systems-fail/&#34;&gt;Understanding How Complex Systems Fail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
