<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analysis | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/analysis/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>analysis</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>analysis</title>
      <link>/tags/analysis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Down the Components of a Post-incident Review</title>
      <link>/post/breaking-down-the-components-of-a-post-incident-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/breaking-down-the-components-of-a-post-incident-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You now know what a post-incident review is, its role in the incident response
process, and when it should be conducted. In this unit, you’ll dive a little
deeper into the details of what makes a post-incident review most effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because incidents differ, the exact makeup of post-incident reviews can be
different, too. But there are some common characteristics and components of a
good review that can provide you with a solid foundation for carrying out the
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-its-not&#34;&gt;What it’s not&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you can understand the characteristics that make for a good post-incident
review, you should consider what it’s &lt;em&gt;not.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a document or report.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s easy to think of a “review” as a
written summary, and indeed, a summary report often follows a post-incident
review. However, these are two different and distinct parts of the Analysis
phase of the incident response lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a determination of causality.&lt;/strong&gt; Your review will look at the
factors that contributed to the failure, but the purpose isn’t to pinpoint a
culprit. It’s to think about and share information about all aspects of the
incident in order to learn and improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a list of action items.&lt;/strong&gt; You may end up with such a list as a
result of what you learn in the review, but this isn’t the focus. If you
don’t come away with a stepwise punch list but you do know more about your
systems than before, the review was successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incident review is, more than anything, a &lt;em&gt;conversation.&lt;/em&gt; It’s a defined
space within which your team can review what they knew at the time and what they
know now, and explore and better understand how the parts of the system –
including the human parts – do or don’t work together in response to problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;characteristics-and-components&#34;&gt;Characteristics and components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good incident review is, first and foremost, &lt;em&gt;blameless.&lt;/em&gt; Although you need to
examine how the human parts of the system interacted with it, you don’t do this
in order to label anyone “at fault.” The focus should be on the failures of the
technology and the process, not of the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frame your questions to reflect this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What was the deficit in your monitoring that failed to give the person at the
keyboard the necessary context to make the right decision?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why was there a &lt;strong&gt;delete the entire database&lt;/strong&gt; option in the tool that didn’t ask
for confirmation?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things go wrong, it can be tempting to point fingers. However, you must
remember this key point: &lt;em&gt;You can’t fire your way to reliability.&lt;/em&gt; Shaming and
blaming and an investigation that’s aimed at finding and firing the person who
is “responsible” won’t lead to more reliable systems. Instead, it will lead to
an inexperienced operations team and personnel who are afraid to act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approach the review as a search for knowledge and context, not a hunt for who
did what and a reaction to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the review is about the failures of the technology, it’s not a
technical process as much as it is a people process. Talk – and more important,
listen – to the people who were involved in the incident. Keep an open mind.
Different people have different perspectives and not everyone will agree, and
that mix of perspectives is invaluable to the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post-incident review is an honest inquiry. As such, it embraces these key
components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discourse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These “4 Ds” create a framework on which you can build a post-incident learning
review that can result in more reliable systems and more productive teams that
work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/running-a-post-incident-review/&#34;&gt;Running a Post-incident Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the Post-incident Review</title>
      <link>/post/defining-the-post-incident-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/defining-the-post-incident-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To conduct a good post-incident review, you must first ensure that everyone is
on the same page. Toward that end, remember that language matters; there are
terms you should use and some you shouldn’t. Key points in conducting the review
are who to include (everyone) and when to do it (within twenty-four to
thirty-six hours). This will help you accomplish the purpose of the review: to
learn and improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learn from incidents by conducting a post-incident review, which happens
during the analysis phase. You should do a post-incident review after every
significant incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Placeholder: graphic of incident response lifecycle in Slide #28)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the formal review takes place after the response and remediation
phases, you begin to set the stage for your analysis as soon as you receive an
actionable alert that an incident has occurred, inform team members, and begin a
conversation around the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language-matters&#34;&gt;Language matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conducting that conversation, and as you go through this unit, there is an
important point that you need to keep in mind: &lt;em&gt;language matters.&lt;/em&gt; There are
specific terms that you should use and others that you should deliberately avoid
using. That’s because the words you use affect how you think about what happened
and can dramatically impact what and how much you learn from the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been shown by research in safety-critical industries such as aviation,
medicine, search and rescue, firefighting, and more. This field of research is
known as resilience engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resilience engineering principles are applicable to the technology sector, as
well. In this module, you’ll learn some of the useful concepts from resilience
engineering, including four of the most common traps people fall into when
attempting to learn from failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-the-post-incident-review&#34;&gt;Defining the post-incident review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone uses exactly the same language to refer to the results of the
analysis phase. You might call it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-incident review&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-incident learning review&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postmortem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retrospective&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, not everyone goes about it in exactly the same way. For example,
many people start by getting everyone who had any connection to the incident
into a room, while other people choose to create the review via individual
interviews and then report back to the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter method often works better when group settings in your organization
are more difficult because of group dynamics or personalities or may be based on
how distributed the group member are, or the type of incident. You should do
what works best for your team and the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever you call it and however you organize it, there are a couple of key
points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inclusiveness:&lt;/strong&gt; You should try to include in the post-incident review
&lt;em&gt;everyone who was involved&lt;/em&gt; in the incident response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timing&lt;/strong&gt;: you should perform the post-incident review &lt;em&gt;within twenty-four
to thirty-six hours&lt;/em&gt; after the event if at all possible. Neuroscience has
confirmed that human memory is notoriously unreliable; people forget things.
The more time that passes after an event, the less detailed and specific
memories tend to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;purpose-of-the-post-incident-review&#34;&gt;Purpose of the post-incident review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the post-incident review is so your team can learn and improve. You
will want to learn about the systems and about the things that you had put in
place that worked or didn’t work, so you can make improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, you should remember that action items that you generate –
reports, tasks, feedback – are useful but are peripheral to the point of the
process, which is to learn and improve. Action items are a secondary effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/breaking-down-the-components-of-a-post-incident-review/&#34;&gt;Breaking Down the Components of a Post-incident Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing Prevention and Preparation</title>
      <link>/post/distinguishing-prevention-and-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/distinguishing-prevention-and-preparation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably heard all your life the adage, attributed to Benjamin Franklin,
that “an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure.” The accepted meaning is
that it’s better to keep a problem from happening than to fix it after it’s
happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your efforts to achieve a high level of reliability for your systems and
services, you should do everything possible to prevent incidents from occurring.
However, due to the complexity of those systems, as explained above, prevention
isn’t always possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, you must take a two-pronged approach to failure: prevention on the one
hand, and when that isn’t possible, preparation to respond – quickly and
effectively. These two are interlinked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of why it’s essential to do both: Sometimes an organization
will deploy an automated system. It works well. In fact, it works almost too
well – because people may take for granted that it will always work. They don’t
make proper preparation for the day that it doesn’t work. When that day comes –
as it inevitably will, sooner or later – and the system fails, it fails
spectacularly, and it’s much harder for operators to understand what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The systems you work on are made up of more than the technology. In fact, you
don’t work “on” or “with” a system; you work &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; the system. You are part of
the system. Complex systems include both technical components (hardware,
software) and human components (people – and their personalities, training, and
knowledge).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How the humans respond when things go wrong is as important as preventing things
from going wrong in the first place. We learn from failure to respond faster and
better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/defining-the-post-incident-review/&#34;&gt;Defining the Post-incident Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Common Traps</title>
      <link>/post/examining-common-traps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/examining-common-traps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we delve into our post-incident review, we need to be on guard against some
human tendencies that can lead us to inaccurate or incomplete conclusions and
distract us from accomplishing the core purpose of the review: learning about
our systems so as to improve their reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you have a roadmap help you get started on the post-incident review process,
but it would also be useful to know about some of the obstacles you might
encounter on this journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning from your own mistakes is something everyone should all do, but you
don’t always have to experience something first-hand to learn from it. Learning
from the mistakes of others, without criticizing or judging them, allows you to
benefit from those lessons without personally suffering the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit, you’ll find out about some common traps that others have fallen
into during the post-incident review process and how to avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trap-1-attribution-to-human-error&#34;&gt;Trap 1: Attribution to “human error”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trap-2-counterfactual-reasoning&#34;&gt;Trap 2: Counterfactual reasoning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trap-3-normative-language&#34;&gt;Trap 3: Normative language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trap-4-mechanistic-reasoning&#34;&gt;Trap 4: Mechanistic reasoning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-attribution-of-human-error/&#34;&gt;Examining Attribution of Human Error&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Counter-factual Reasoning</title>
      <link>/post/examining-counter-factual-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/examining-counter-factual-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the field of psychology, counterfactual thinking is a concept that’s
associated with the human tendency to invent possible alternatives to past
events – how things might have turned out differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterfactual&lt;/em&gt; means “contrary to facts,” and &lt;em&gt;counterfactual reasoning&lt;/em&gt;
refers to telling a story about events that did not happen, in order to explain
the events that did. You can identify counterfactual statements by key phrases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failed to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If only&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of counterfactual statements related to post-incident reviews:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The monitoring system failed to detect the problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The engineer did not check the validity of the configuration before enacting
it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This could have been picked up in the canary environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this type of reasoning is that you’re talking about things that
didn’t happen instead of taking the time to understand how what did happen,
happened. You don’t learn anything from this speculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-mechanistic-reasoning/&#34;&gt;Examining Mechanistic Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Mechanistic Reasoning</title>
      <link>/post/examining-mechanistic-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/examining-mechanistic-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mechanistic reasoning&lt;/em&gt; refers to the concept that a particular outcome can be
inferred from intervention. It’s sometimes called the &lt;em&gt;meddling kids syndrome&lt;/em&gt;
based on the premise that “Our system would have worked fine … if it hadn’t been
for those meddling kids.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you use mechanistic reasoning in your post-incident review, you build your
conclusions on the fallacy that the systems you work with and within are
basically working correctly, and if only those “meddling kids” hadn’t done
whatever they did, the failure would not have occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not how systems work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this point, imagine the following scenario: You work on a
production service. Now you’re told that you are not allowed to touch or do
anything to that service. Everything outside your team continues as before –
customers continue to use the service, external dependencies continue to change,
the Internet functions normally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can’t make any changes to the code or configuration. No deployments, no
control plane operations, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you think your service would still be running as expected after a day? After
a week? After a month? After a year? How long could you realistically expect
your service to keep running without human intervention?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Human adaptive capacity is necessary to keep our systems up and running&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason your systems are up and running in the first place is because of
the actions of humans in the control loop. It’s only through human action
and ability to adapt to changing circumstances that the system continues to
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it’s erroneous to conclude the system was “basically working…
if it hadn’t been for those meddling kids.” In fact, the reliability of your
service is not independent of the humans who work on it. Instead, it’s a direct
result of the work that the humans do on it every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with mechanistic reasoning is that it leads you down a path where
you believe that finding the faulty human is equivalent to finding the problem.
However, that same faulty human has been improvising and adapting to keep the
system running for weeks and months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-normative-language/&#34;&gt;Examining Normative Language&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Normative Language</title>
      <link>/post/examining-normative-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/examining-normative-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Normativity&lt;/em&gt; relates to the human tendency to designate some actions and
outcomes as desirable or good and other actions or outcomes as undesirable or
bad. A norm is a standard of correctness agreed upon by a society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you use normative language in a post-incident review, you judge the
decisions and actions of those responding to the incident with the benefit of
&lt;em&gt;hindsight&lt;/em&gt;. This language implies that there was an obviously correct course of
action that the operator should have followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normative language can usually be identified by adverbs such as “inadequately,”
“carelessly,” “hastily,” and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normative thinking leads you to judge decisions based on their outcomes. This
isn’t logical because the outcome is the &lt;em&gt;only piece of information that was not
available&lt;/em&gt; to those who made the decisions and judgments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with normative thinking is that you neglect to understand how the
actions of the operators made sense to them at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/&#34;&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining the Attribution of Human Error</title>
      <link>/post/examining-attribution-of-human-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/examining-attribution-of-human-error/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Humans make mistakes. However, &lt;em&gt;human error&lt;/em&gt; is not a diagnosis; it’s a symptom.
When human error is deemed to be the reason for a failure, you may stop there
instead of further analyzing the incident to determine the &lt;em&gt;root cause –&lt;/em&gt; which
is a deeper, systemic issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;System design, organizational context, and personal context all affect when, how
and with what impact people make mistakes. &lt;em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Human error&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; is a label that
causes you to quit investigating at precisely the moment when you’re about to
discover something interesting about your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with the “human error” conclusion in investigations is that it
causes you to lose sight of the fact that what the humans did made sense to them
at the time. Mistakes, by definition, aren’t deliberate, so they didn’t intend
to make a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we see or hear “human error”, it is a signal that we need to look deeper.
Root cause analysis is needed to identify the sequence of events that resulted
in the human error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-counter-factual-reasoning/&#34;&gt;Examining Counter-factural Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Fear of Incidents</title>
      <link>/post/exploring-fear-of-incidents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/exploring-fear-of-incidents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There is also a subtler effect, which is that the fear of on-call is often enough by itself to radically change people’s behavior. Entire development teams reject outright the notion of going on call, because of the impact on their personal lives, family, and in-hours effectiveness.&amp;rdquo; - Niall Murphy, Microsoft &amp;ldquo;Seeking SRE&amp;rdquo;(O&amp;rsquo;Reilly)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, we downplay the significance of an outage &amp;hellip; or worse &amp;hellip; intentionally mis-label or not report a disruption in service for fear of reprimand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, we have felt that incidents reflected poorly in several areas of our engineering efforts and the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has not been until more recently through many of the conversations around devops and site reliability engineering, that we are starting to rethink incidents and now view them as opportunities to learn and improve our systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/exploring-why-incidents-are-unexpected/&#34;&gt;Exploring Why Incidents Are Unexpected&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Subjectivity of Incidents</title>
      <link>/post/exploring-subjectivity-of-incidents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/exploring-subjectivity-of-incidents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you ask engineers across different organizations and industries, you will get many different answers about what an incident is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is only when a customer is affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others will label disruptions as incidents even if a customer never experienced a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subjectivity is an unfortunate property of incidents in a lot of cases, even when it comes to identifying severity levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/exploring-fear-of-incidents/&#34;&gt;Exploring Fear of Incidents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gathering Data For the Post-incident Review</title>
      <link>/post/gathering-data-for-the-post-incident-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/gathering-data-for-the-post-incident-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The post-incident review process begins with the data. That includes the data in
the conversations related to the incident as well as the data collected by
monitoring systems. You can use Azure tools to collect, find, correlate, and
share the data in the course of conducting your learning review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit, you’ll learn how to go about the construction of a shared,
accurate chronology that reflects the non-linear nature of an incident.
&lt;em&gt;Non-linear&lt;/em&gt; refers to the fact that incidents are almost never just a matter of
“this happened, and then that happened, then we noticed, then we did something,
and then we were done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an incident occurs, develops, and plays out, different people get involved.
They notice and try different things, and some work, some don’t. If multiple
people are working at the same time, all these things can be happening
simultaneously. Thus, it’s a bit more complicated than just a straight-line
description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a logical timeline, then, you need a starting point and the place to
start is with the relevant data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gather-the-data&#34;&gt;Gather the data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you can conduct a learning review, you first need to gather data.
Specifically, you need to collect as much of the conversation surrounding the
event as you can so you can use all of the crucial data contained in it. The
conversation among team members that happened during the outage or incident will
be one of your richest sources of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also should gather from your monitoring system and other places from which
the people involved in the incident drew context. What information were they
getting from your systems when the incident was going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, if possible, it would be helpful for you to get a better picture of
what changed just prior to and during the incident because changes are often
contributing factors when an incident occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data-gathering step has three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collect the conversation.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s important to have a place for people to
communicate and share what worked and what failed, what they’re hesitant to
try, what they’ve tried in the past. This conversation between the people as
they work through and solve the issue is your best source of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine the context.&lt;/strong&gt; This is done primarily through monitoring. It
involves building a point in time to collect the data you have and correlate
it to the event now that you’re looking back at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find the changes.&lt;/strong&gt; You do this through activity and audits logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-collection-tools&#34;&gt;Data collection tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tools that you can use to make these steps easier. Using Azure for
these systems can help make you better able to gather all this data quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure DevOps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have data already captured in the Azure DevOps Boards that includes tracking
of incidents with information about who was on call, who was assigned to the
incident, and so forth. You can also use the Azure DevOps Wiki as a centralized
way to pull in some of the pieces of information about both the incident itself
and the conversation that happened during the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graph Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also use queries in Graph Explorer to programmatically find, export and
bring in the conversation that was collected inside the Teams channel that was
devoted to this specific incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashboards, Application Insights and JSON&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create a dashboard in the Azure portal to correlate what the operators
were seeing to the incident itself. Application Insights give you graphs you can
add to the dashboard to visualize the information. This allows you to see your
tracked metrics side-by-side to better identify where and when the incident
happened. You can pull down the dashboard and its components using JSON, and,
for example, focus on a specific window of time and drill down to provide more
context for your investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log Analytics and Audit Log&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use information here to discover changes and find the delta between
where you started and where you ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/reviewing-azures-monitoring-tools/&#34;&gt;Reviewing Azure Monitoring Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Incident Analysis Phase</title>
      <link>/post/identifying-the-incident-analysis-phase/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/identifying-the-incident-analysis-phase/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The post-incident review is where the idea of incidents begin to shift from things that are feared and avoided to things that can provide valuable information to a team and business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely will you find a business today that doesn&amp;rsquo;t heavily rely on digital services to earn and keep customers. There are going to be problems along the way. Not only that, but customers expect improvements, technology changes, competitors get smarter. There are fewer and fewer industries that can maintain the status quo and continue to exist, let alone prosper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis phase allows for an honest and open retrospective discussion about what took place. We as an organization want to understand the realities of the scenario from an objective perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly how you conduct the exercises will vary but the focus of the conversation is on what and how things happened rather than who and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By identifying the incident timeline as well as the specific highlights, people can identify the beginning and end of each phase, including the conversations that took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helps isolate specific areas of improvements such as moving away from using email distribution lists as the default channel and method of delivering actionable alerts. In discussions about the detection phase, it seemed clear to everyone that the problem could have been solved sooner had they known about it sooner. Sometimes even small changes can have a huge impact on improving the overall time to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how businesses choose to perform their post-incident review, they should take place no more than 36-48 hours after the incident has concluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking to collect as much objective data as well as testimonial from a diverse set of perspectives. It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to remember what took place in much detail after a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If possible, the exercise should be facilitated by someone that was not involved in the incident. Someone who can remove themselves from the timeline of events and perspectives of what took place. Objective data is often easier to obtain when someone else asks the questions and encourages an honest conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of a post-incident review isn&amp;rsquo;t to end up with a document or artifact that the meeting took place. It&amp;rsquo;s not an exploration on what definitively caused the issue in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our systems are always changing. That&amp;rsquo;s just where we are today. Businesses that are providing some kind of service to their customers where technology is involved are required to make constant changes. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if it&amp;rsquo;s in the cloud, data center, or closet, servers need improvements and replacements. Operating systems need patches and upgrades. Applications need to be updated and restarted. Databases and logs are changing and growing. Networks are coming and going. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on and it&amp;rsquo;s often difficult to put our thumb on exactly what&amp;rsquo;s causing what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, it&amp;rsquo;s ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the advantage of examining incidents in phases means that regardless to the problems we experience in the future, we know that we can detect a problem, get the right people involved, and recover services faster than before. We are prepared for the infinite world of possibilities we like to call the &amp;ldquo;unknown unknowns&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This takes us to our final phase of the incident lifecycle, readiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/identifying-the-incident-readiness-phase&#34;&gt;Identifying the Readiness Phase of an Incident&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying The Scribe</title>
      <link>/post/identifying-the-scribe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/identifying-the-scribe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The scribe’s role is to document the conversation in as much detail as possible. Teams commonly use phone bridges, conference calls, or video chat to get everyone together and try to understand what is going on, which can certainly help create space for the conversation. However, it is difficult for us to go through and understand in detail what the engineers were saying and doing unless it is transcribed. As a result, a scribe is that person who can help us document as much as possible to review later. What were people saying, doing, feeling, and even experiencing?  It is all data to be analyzed – but only if we capture it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/identifying-the-subject-matter-experts/&#34;&gt;Identifying the Subject Matter Experts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running a Post-incident Review</title>
      <link>/post/running-a-post-incident-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/running-a-post-incident-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We want to develop a sense making approach to the present situation in order to act upon it better in the future&amp;hellip; in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different ways to conduct a useful post-incident review, but there are
some common practices that can make the process easier and more effective. If
you run a facilitated review meeting, keep your review and planning meetings
separate, ask better questions, and identify how things went right, you can
learn more and use what you learn to improve the reliability of your systems,
services, and processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re aware of some of the common pitfalls that can sabotage your
post-incident review, and you know what &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to do. The next logical question
is “what should you do instead?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this unit, you’ll learn about four helpful practices that can make your
response team better and improve the post-incident analysis process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-1-run-a-facilitated-post-incident-review&#34;&gt;Practice 1: Run a facilitated post-incident review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You already know that a post-incident review is not a document or report, so it
follows that having one person write up a “postmortem” of what happened doesn’t
make for a helpful post-incident review. No matter how knowledgeable or how
deeply involved in the incident that person might be, not much will be learned
if everything comes from a single viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting those who were involved in the incident together at the same time is the
first step. But there is something else you can do to increase the useful
learning that comes out of the review even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;facilitator&lt;/em&gt; is someone or something that makes an action or process easier.
To make the post-incident review process both easier and more effective, you
should plan to have a post-incident review meeting with a &lt;em&gt;neutral facilitator&lt;/em&gt;
– someone who was not involved in the response to this incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone will learn more if the facilitator cannot be seen to have any
preconceived ideas or a personal agenda in telling the story of the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact format for the meeting will depend on your team, scheduling, and the
nature of the incident, but here are some more basic guidelines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings, not marathons:&lt;/strong&gt; the meetings don’t have to be long. Generally,
sixty to ninety minutes is the maximum length of time most people can fully
concentrate and participate effectively, so limit the meeting to not more
than an hour and a half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre&lt;/strong&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;meeting prep:&lt;/strong&gt; to make better use of the meeting time, it can be
helpful for the facilitator to prepare by conducting one-to-one interviews
with some of the members of the response team to get an overview of the
incident and ideas about which topics to talk about in the meeting.
Individual interviews are also appropriate with certain personalities, when
presenting in front of the room is a cause for discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not required for every incident&lt;/strong&gt;: this is a learning process, and you’re
“learning to learn,” so start small. You don’t have to do this for every
incident. You can pick and choose. You might want to start with smaller
incidents or start with a review meeting only once per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-incident review meeting is an opportunity to find out what went wrong,
what was done right, and how failures can be handled better in the future. The
ultimate goal is to improve reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-2-ask-better-questions&#34;&gt;Practice 2: Ask better questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You already know that language matters, and in the post-incident review, this
applies especially to the questions you ask. Objective questions will usually
elicit more useful answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In particular, it’s better to ask people “how” or “what” instead of “why.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people are asked to explain “why” they did something or “why” something
happened, it tends to put them on the defensive. Beginning a question with “why”
often comes across as a judgement, criticism, or accusation. It forces people to
justify their actions, and people don’t always know why they did something, or
why something happened as a result of their actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean you can’t explore the reasons the incident occurred or the
reasoning a person used to decide what to do in response to it. It just means
you should pay attention to how you word those questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t ask “why did you do that?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, ask “&lt;em&gt;what factored into your decision to make that change?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t ask “why wasn’t this caught in canary?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, ask “&lt;em&gt;how effective is canary at catching this sort of issue,
usually?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that the post-incident review is about learning. Each participant in
the incident is likely to have had a slightly different view on events. You’ll
learn more if you ask questions that expose these multiple views and
interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get tunnel vision. Sometimes focusing too narrowly on the incident in
question will cause you to miss valuable information. You will often learn as
much by asking about how work “normally” happens as you will by asking about the
specific incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about how to ask better questions, check out this resource:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://extfiles.etsy.com/DebriefingFacilitationGuide.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Etsy Debriefing Facilitation
Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-3-ask-how-things-went-right&#34;&gt;Practice 3: Ask how things went right&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you think about learning from failure, you may forget that even within a
major outage or other incident, in addition to the things that go wrong there
are also things that go right. Far from our view of incidents as one-offs or
products of extreme conditions, in most complex systems things go wrong for many
of the same reasons they go right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s human nature to focus your questions on the negative side of the equation.
However, also asking about how things went right will provide you with insights
that you would not have gotten otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don’t just ask how the outage happened.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ask how your team recovered the systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to know what insights, tools, skills, and people helped in the recovery
effort. These are things you want to be able to reproduce, so this information
will be valuable in planning what to do going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context, you want to ask how people came to know what they knew and on
what basis they made the decisions they made. Was there a critical moment when
someone shared a piece of information that helped unlock the puzzle of what was
happening? How did they know to do that? Where did the information come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for themes and patterns. Finally, as part of recognizing what went right,
ask &lt;em&gt;What do you know now that you didn’t know previously?&lt;/em&gt; If learning resulted
from the incident and from the incident response and review processes, that’s
another thing that went right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-4-keep-review-and-planning-meetings-separate&#34;&gt;Practice 4: Keep review and planning meetings separate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you’ve resolved the immediate incident, you’re naturally going to want to
talk about repair items and future mitigation – and you should – but these
topics should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be a part of your post-incident review meeting. Your
post-incident review meeting has a purpose and allowing the discussion of repair
items into that meeting will distract from that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best plan is to discuss repair items and planning issues in a separate
meeting a day or two after your post-incident review. You might want to do this
with a smaller group. Both of the meetings will be more productive as a result
of this separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will help you keep the focus of the post-incident review where it belongs, on
what actually happened. In addition, allowing a day or two of “soak time” will
result in better “synthesis,” giving your subconscious time to work on the
issues. This will help you to identify the most “energy-efficient” repair items
– those that require minimum energy for maximum impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/gathering-data-for-the-post-incident-review/&#34;&gt;Gathering Data for the Post-incident Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Why We Learn From Incidents</title>
      <link>/post/understanding-why-we-learn-from-incidents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/understanding-why-we-learn-from-incidents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Incident response doesn’t stop when the incident is over. They say those who
don’t study history are doomed to repeat it. Likewise, those who don’t study,
analyze, and learn from the incidents they resolved are doomed to keep repeating
the process, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your most important means of learning from incidents is the post-incident
review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an incident occurs, your first reaction probably isn’t, “Hurray – a
learning opportunity!” Your immediate priority is figuring out what went wrong
and fixing it as quickly as possible, to reduce the impact on your customers and
end users – as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once the incident has been resolved, it’s important to follow up and
benefit from the discovery of whatever mistakes or circumstances led to the
failure. Doing so will help you prevent the same thing from happening again and
will also help you understand what tactics do and don’t work best when
responding to any kind of incident in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-incident review is part of the analysis phase of the incident response
lifecycle. Not all post-incident reviews are created equal. There are different
ways to approach the process, and too much focus on certain aspects of the
problem or framing questions in the wrong way can reduce the value of the
review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to now explore the best path towards generating actionable introspection about the systems we co-create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/understanding-how-complex-systems-fail/&#34;&gt;Understanding How Complex Systems Fail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
