<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sre | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/sre/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/sre/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>sre</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>sre</title>
      <link>/tags/sre/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining Site Reliability Engineering</title>
      <link>/post/defining-site-reliability-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/defining-site-reliability-engineering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Site Reliability Engineering is an engineering discipline devoted to helping
organizations sustainably achieve the appropriate level of reliability in their
systems, services, and products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key concepts to take away from this definition are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliability.&lt;/strong&gt; You learned in the introductory module that there are
multiple aspects to reliability and later in this module, you’ll examine
each in more detail. You also learned about the importance of reliability –
why it matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustainability.&lt;/strong&gt; In this context, “sustainable” refers to the role of
people in creating a sustainable operations practice. Reliable systems,
services, products are built by people. It is crucial to the concept of SRE
to implement an operations practice that is sustainable over time, so that
people are able to bring their best to the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appropriateness.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s important to understand that 100% reliability
isn’t often possible, especially in today’s complex systems with
dependencies on other systems. 100% reliability means zero down time, which
also means no opportunity to make any changes or improvements that could
create some down time. Instead of striving for a goal of absolute
reliability, determine the appropriate level of reliability for a particular
application or service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of a site reliability engineer bridges the span between operations and
development but also goes beyond DevOps, and the SRE philosophy is the basis of
a new and more efficient and effective approach to building and operating
reliable systems and applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
