<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>monitoring | On Call Life</title>
    <link>/tags/monitoring/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>monitoring</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>monitoring</title>
      <link>/tags/monitoring/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring For Operational Awareness</title>
      <link>/post/monitoring-for-operational-awareness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/monitoring-for-operational-awareness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sustainably achieving an appropriate level of reliability first requires that you know what’s going on with your systems and services. You find that out by monitoring. Before you can effectively monitor for reliability, however, you must have a reasonable level of operational awareness. This means you need to
understand how systems in production are functioning in order to work toward reliability of those systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/monitoring-for-operational-awareness/operational-awareness.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s production environments and the paths by which we deploy systems and applications are complex. Thus, it is not uncommon to have to do a bit of discovery to obtain an operational awareness baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some questions to ask include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What exactly is running in production?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a specific application, what are its component parts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of those parts communicate with which other parts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some more complex factors that you’ll want to examine to give you a better understanding of your systems and services and how to make them more reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the app or service perform in the past?&lt;/strong&gt; It’s true that “past
performance is no guarantee of future results.” However, knowledge about
past performance can be useful in calibrating expectations, and awareness of
past outages can provide you with a sense of potential failure modes that
you should incorporate into your thought processes around reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the socio-technical context?&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, who owns or cares
about the service or app? How did it get deployed? Information about the
stakeholders, as well as knowing, for example, whether it was deployed by
hand or via an automated process can have many ramifications when we begin
to make updates to improve reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to all these questions will help you to build a baseline around “normal” behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/monitoring-for-reliability/&#34;&gt;Monitoring For Reliability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring For Reliability</title>
      <link>/post/monitoring-for-reliability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/monitoring-for-reliability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The world today is extremely connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital services have become so embedded in our daily lives that when they become unavailable, it often has an adverse effect on our own livelihoods. Like electricity and running water, we don&amp;rsquo;t realize our reliance on it until it&amp;rsquo;s suddenly unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;monitoring&#34;&gt;Monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitoring is a way of collecting information about what is going on in your systems so you can improve things as well as make objectively informed decisions. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-monitor/overview/?wt_mc_id=oncalllife-blog-jahand&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Azure Monitor&lt;/a&gt; is an example of tooling that allows this type of collection and analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many aspects of a system can be monitored. From the component level (CPU, Memory) to business impact and everything in between. We might gauge performance, examine security, or (in our case) evaluate and improve reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reliability&#34;&gt;Reliability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When monitoring for reliability, we are trying to proactively manage not only the availability of a service, but many aspects of reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the service and the expectations of the end user, some aspects of reliability may be more valuable than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Exercise:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Discuss and document perceived expectations users have regarding the reliability of your service?
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To determine what to monitor, continue with  
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-all-aspects-of-reliability/&#34;&gt;Examinging All Aspects of Reliability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing Azure&#39;s Monitoring Tools</title>
      <link>/post/reviewing-azures-monitoring-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/reviewing-azures-monitoring-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Azure Monitor includes a number of features and tools you can use to monitor and
measure reliability, using data from many different sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article’s focus is to help you keep your “eyes on the prize” – the goal of
improving reliability in your organization. You should now understand what
reliability is and why it’s important. You know that operational awareness is an
essential precursor to monitoring for reliability, and that you need to
establish a baseline of “normal” behavior as a first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’ll look at the practical question of how to go about doing that. As with
all complex tasks, the right tools can help you get the job done more quickly
and easily. In this unit, you’ll get a quick introduction to Azure Monitor,
Application Insights, and Log Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;azure-monitor&#34;&gt;Azure Monitor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azure Monitor is a comprehensive platform for monitoring Azure resources to gain
insights into your applications, infrastructure, and network. In this module,
the focus will be on the Azure Monitor tools that you can use to monitor and
measure reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at Azure Monitor starts with the data that comes into the system. Azure
Monitor takes in data from a number of different sources. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data from applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data from the various operating systems running in Azure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information fed from Azure resources, subscriptions, and tenants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Custom data of any sort and from any source&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many things we can do with that information: analyze it, visualize it,
integrate it, and respond to it when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-types&#34;&gt;Data types&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data that comes into Azure Monitor can be divided into two types:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metrics:&lt;/strong&gt; small numerical pieces of information from counters, gauges,
and so forth that are collected on a regular basis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log data:&lt;/strong&gt; information gathered from many different logs such as Windows
event logs, Linux syslog, agents running on virtual machines, custom logs,
telemetry from Application Insights, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this module, we will be focusing primarily on log data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create, import, and export dashboards, using JSON files, to help you
better visualize the data and provide you with operational awareness about all
aspects of your Azure subscription, including reliability information. You can
also set access controls on the dashboards and share them with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/examining-common-traps/&#34;&gt;Examining Common Traps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
